<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <letters author="Marian Baldwin">
        <letter>
            <when type="DATE" date="1917-7-8">July 8th, 1917</when>
            <!-- hjb: I decided to use a "when" element rather than "date" or "time" because that way I can use the "when" element whenever there was a day of the week, time, date, month, etc. -->
            <p><when type="DOTW" date="1917-7-6">Friday</when> night we entered the war zone at
                    <when type="TIME" time="19:00">seven o'clock</when> but you would never know it.
                Aside from boat-drills and sleeping on deck people act as usual. The officers on the
                boat are very particular about the drills; several times the alarm has sounded and
                we have been taught just what to do in case we are hit. It's very funny to see the
                people rush below for their valuables, strapping on their life preservers as they go
                    <etc type="PARENTHESES">which we always have near at hand wherever we are -on
                    deck or in the saloon</etc>.
                <!-- hjb: although it's not necessary, I decided to give any parenthases or quotation marks an "etc" element just to give it emphasis. -->
                In about five minutes we are lined up, divided into groups in front of our own
                particular life-boats which have been swung out over the sea ready to lower. Every
                one is checked off and each man is told what woman he is to save. <etc
                    type="PARENTHESES">Great excitement at this point as no one of the men wants to
                    save the lady detailed to him, but some one in another boat!</etc> We all stand
                about looking too absurd and bumping into each other's life preservers on the
                crowded upper deck. Finally the signal is given which releases us, and we all file
                down again to take off the clumsy heavy jackets of safety and regale ourselves with
                various amusements on the deck.</p>

            <p>Rumor has it that two ships have been sunk, one in the course ahead of where we were
                    <when type="SAYING" date="1917-7-7">yesterday</when> and the other about an hour
                behind us. No one knows how many lives were lost. Perhaps those three submarines
                were more fact than fiction after all.</p>

            <p>It is thought that we should make <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Bordeaux"
                    >Bordeaux</loc>
                <!-- hjb: a location element ("loc" for short) is used to indicate where Marian is talking about, whether it be a contry or city. -->
                by <when type="DOTW" date="1917-7-10">Tuesday</when> morning if all goes well and
                that the convoy which should have met us days ago will be with us <when
                    type="SAYING" date="1917-7-8">to-night</when>.</p>

            <p>This being <when type="DOTW" date="1917-7-8">Sunday</when>, the boys on board are
                very much dressed up, that is to say they are wearing clean shirts and have their
                hair brushed! It's a perfect day, warm and cloudless, and I've been lying in the sun
                adding to my coat of tan. We all feel quite sad that the voyage is so nearly over
                -it has been such loads of fun and I shall hate saying good-by to every one.</p>

            <p>
                <name type="BOAT" n="La-Touraine">La Touraine</name>
                <!-- hjb: the "name" element is used for any sort of title and/or name. it is used for boat names, people's names, nationality, buildings, language, etc. -->
            </p>
        </letter>
        <letter>

            <p>En route from <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Bordeaux">Bordeaux</loc> to <loc
                    type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Paris">Paris</loc>, <when type="DATE"
                    date="1917-7-18">July 18th, 1917</when>.</p>

            <p> On landing <when type="SAYING" date="1917-7-17">yesterday</when> I went straight to
                the <name type="BUILDING" n="Hôtel-De-France">Hôtel de France</name> and it
                certainly was good to have room to turn around in: as for a bed with real springs I
                greeted it with enthusiasm! Towards evening <name type="PERSON"
                    n="Frank+Marian-Baldwin">Frank and I</name> took a long walk about the <loc
                    type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Paris">city</loc>. A port town always interests
                me and we saw it all at the loveliest time of day. The harbor was full of fishing
                smacks and small craft of all kinds and exquisite tones in the sails and rigging.
                The last rays of the sun cast a rosy hue over everything, making one think at once
                of <loc type="CITY" country="ITALY" n="Venice">Venice</loc> and the days before the
                war. Later <name type="PERSON" n="Frank+Marian-Baldwin">we</name> wandered through
                some of the oldest parts of <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Bordeaux"
                    >Bordeaux</loc> and I really felt that I was abroad again! The narrow winding
                streets and cobblestones, with here and there an ancient façade or doorway and
                everywhere, in the poorest alleys, a bit of a vine or potted plant in the windows.
                How do they manage to make it all so picturesque and alluring?</p>

            <p>The women and the old men are doing everything and it is surprising to see the lady
                conductors. On this train they use women entirely, even in the dining car. The war
                hasn't robbed them of vivacity or their beautiful complexions and I believe they are
                even prettier in their simple black working clothes than before.</p>

            <p>We are at present passing through the famous vineyards and I have never seen the <loc
                    type="COUNTRY" n="France">country</loc> look so beautiful. The crops seem in
                perfect condition, thanks to the patient labor of these wonderful women, and the
                grain waves in profusion everywhere. I have longed for you at every turn, how you
                would enjoy it all. The poppies are in their prime and, as the train whirls by, they
                look like immense splashes of red -almost like stains of blood against the gold of
                the wheat.</p>

            <p>I have just come in from a very excellent meal in the dining car -the food was served
                promptly by two <name type="NATIONALITY" n="French">French</name> girls of the
                peasant type and with a speed that was wonderful, the car holding over thirty
                persons.</p>

            <p>
                <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Paris">Paris</loc>
            </p>

        </letter>
        <letter>

            <p><loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Bordeaux">Bordeaux</loc>, <when type="DATE"
                    date="1917-12-27">December 27th, 1917</when>.</p>

            <p>Such crowded busy hours as we have put in during the last few days. However, there
                will be a bit of a breathing spell now, as there are to be fewer men in on leave
                until <when type="HOLIDAY" date="1918-01-01">New Year's</when>. This afternoon <name
                    type="PERSON" n="Aunt-T">Aunt T.</name> is coming to see my hideous little room.
                I have built a fire that is much too large for my diminutive fire-place, and we are
                to have tea and cake! So you see it is to be a regular house warming.</p>

            <p>I don't know whether I have written you about my sleeping apartment before. At any
                rate, it is on the top floor of a tall thin house. It was the only place I could get
                and so I have thought it wiser to laugh at its disadvantages. There is no coal, and
                wood costs <d type="₣" amount="6">six francs</d>
                <!-- hjb: the "d" element is used for units of something. --> for <d type="WOOD"
                    amount="8">eight pieces</d> so one just goes without except on special occasions
                like <when type="SAYING" date="1917-12-27">to-day</when>. I generally get in from
                the canteen about <when type="TIME" time="23:30">11:30 P. M.</when> and then my four
                flights seem a bit of a climb, but it is nice to have a little spot of your own and
                I'm always so glad to get to the top of the stairs. I still have struggles with my
                hot water bag, for I can always see my breath in the room and I think <etc
                    type="QUOTATION-MARK">old faithful</etc> has gotten a bit discouraged and
                doesn't think it worth while to keep warm in this damp penetrating clime.</p>

            <p>The room is papered in a mud-colored tone of gold, beetle-shaped figures scattered
                over it at intervals of <d type="in" amount="2">two inches</d>! I have a black iron
                bedstead and a fire-place and mantelpiece made of the black and white mottled marble
                that is used for tombstones! There are two windows, but unfortunately one can't look
                out as they are made of red and navy blue stained glass. However, I am very fond of
                my little room and <when type="SAYING" date="1917-12-27">to-day</when> it wears a
                gay and festive look in anticipation of my party. I have put all my photographs out
                and we are going to have a fine cozy time I know.</p>

        </letter>
        <letter>

            <p>
                <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Aix">Aix</loc>, <when type="DATE"
                    date="1918-5-10">May 10th, 1918</when>.</p>

            <p>I've been very busy <when type="SAYING" date="1918-5-10">to-day</when> learning a new
                dance. The weekly vaudeville troop arrived from <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE"
                    n="Paris">Paris</loc> minus one number and as <name type="PERSON" n="Carrell"
                    >Mr. Carrell</name> and I have danced on several Stunt Night programs, they
                asked us to fill in for the missing number. So we are on for a week and we were so
                thankful that we had something that could be put right on to fill in. This little
                taste of stage life under such delightful auspices, is great fun. I have a dressing
                room all my own, No. 5, and <name type="PERSON" n="Alice">Alice</name> has been an
                angel, acts as maid and helps me change my costume between our two numbers. We are
                billed with the professionals all over town,<etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">Miss Baldwin
                    &amp; <name type="PERSON" n="Carrell">Mr. Carrell</name>.</etc> It looked too
                absurd.</p>

            <p>I come on right after the <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">trained cats</etc> and, while
                waiting in the wings, dodge the <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">snake charmer's</etc>
                serpents! She has two about <d type="yd" amount="12">twelve yards</d> long apiece
                and they wriggle and glide around behind the stage and appear suddenly in the most
                unexpected manner! The snake charmer keeps them between times rolled up neatly in a
                lunch basket with a cloth drawn tightly over the top! One of the acrobats told me
                she doped them. Sometimes I get so interested behind the scenes that I almost forget
                to go on when my turn comes. These vaudeville artists are the most kind-hearted of
                mortals and have been so good to me and encouraged me in the nicest way the first
                night, telling me to <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">keep smiling and not be
                    scared.</etc> One comedian has been especially good to me. -He white-washes his
                face and wears a green nose and a suit with huge black and white checks!</p>

        </letter>
        <letter>

            <p><loc type="COMMUNE" country="FRANCE" n="Baccarat">Baccarat</loc>, <when type="DATE"
                    date="1918-7-15">July 15th, 1918</when>.</p>

            <p>I am now working in the big new canteen at Headquarters, and believe me, it is one
                busy place. I'm on duty only eight hours a day but during that time I work like mad
                and scarcely have time to breathe. There is a line that files in and past our
                counter and then out through a farther door. That line never stops from the time we
                are open in the morning until it gets dark at night. I am kept hopping like a
                grass-hopper and bed looks pretty good to me at the end of the day. It's a fine life
                though, just work and food and sleep and I am thriving and growing fat on it!</p>

            <p>We are at present attached to the 77th Division which is, as you know, the <loc
                    type="STATE" country="UNITED STATES" n="New York">New York</loc> drafted bunch.
                It is, I believe, a unique division and to me a most interesting one. It looks as
                though they had taken a cross section of <loc type="CITY" country="UNITED STATES"
                    n="New York City">New York City</loc> and divided it into Battalions, Regiments,
                Companies and all the different units and branches of the service which go to make
                up a division. The officers are almost entirely from the <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK"
                    >four hundred</etc> so called, and the enlisted men from the lower East Side,
                    <name type="NATIONALITY" n="Italian">Italians</name>, <name type="NATIONALITY"
                    n="Polish-Jew">Polish Jews</name>, <name type="NATIONALITY" n="Greek"
                    >Greeks</name>, <name type="NATIONALITY" n="Serbian">Serbs</name>, in fact,
                representatives from most every country in the world. Many of them can't even speak
                    <name type="LANGUAGE" n="English">English</name> intelligibly and I have been
                thankful for my scraps of <name type="LANGUAGE" n="Italian">Italian</name>, <name
                    type="LANGUAGE" n="French">French</name> and even <name type="LANGUAGE"
                    n="German">German</name> to make them understand me. They are a ferocious
                looking lot for the most part and always sure that I am trying to skin them. It's
                rather pathetic and I try to be patient and make them understand that the <name
                    type="ORG" n="YMCA">Y</name> may have made mistakes unintentionally but that we
                are not in <loc type="COUNTRY" n="France">France</loc> to profiteer. It's a bit
                discouraging at the end of a long hot day to have some boy throw the change you have
                given him down on the counter and announce in a loud voice that the <etc
                    type="QUOTATION-MARK">Y girl</etc> is trying to cheat him. They haven't learned
                the value of <d type="₣">French money</d>, not having been over here long and are
                tremendously suspicious of what they call <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">that tin <d
                        type="¥">Chinese money</d></etc>
                <etc type="PARENTHESES">the <name type="NATIONALITY" n="French">French</name> have
                    punctured their smaller coins in the center in order to save metal</etc> and are
                always sure that you are trying to put something over on them. However, there are
                many who make up for the disagreeable ones. Two or three <name type="NATIONALITY"
                    n="Irish">Irish</name> lads with merry blue eyes and the most alluring of
                brogues are generally hanging over the end of the counter and are very much my
                friends. They are always right on the spot when there is a case of tobacco to be
                opened or heavy things to lift and have even helped me squeeze lemons! The work is a
                never ceasing joy to me on account of these bright spots and many others that turn
                up constantly to make me happier than I have ever been in my life. No one who hasn't
                tried it, knows what a satisfaction a long day's work can bring. Thank God for the
                opportunity.</p>

        </letter>
        <letter>

            <p><loc type="COMMUNE" country="FRANCE" n="Baccarat">Baccarat</loc>, <when type="DATE"
                    date="1918-7-24">July 24th, 1918</when>.</p>

            <p>A wonderful moon <when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-24">to-night</when> and the
                countryside transformed under its silvery radiance. We have had terrible nights for
                a week now and we are all more or less worn out with little sleep and long hot days.
                The <name type="NATIONALITY" n="German">German</name> planes have been coming over
                as regularly as clock work and as this sector is unimportant compared to others
                farther up the line, we aren't really protected at all. An <name type="NATIONALITY"
                    n="English">English</name> aëroplane field lies some miles in the country behind
                us and they do what they can to help drive off the enemy planes but they aren't able
                to accomplish much as they have a huge area to cover and very little equipment.</p>

            <p>I thought I knew what an air raid was like after being in <loc type="CITY"
                    country="FRANCE" n="Paris">Paris</loc> for <when type="TIME FRAME"
                    from="1917-7-17" to="1917-11-20">six months</when>, but in comparison, those
                raids seem like mere child's play. Ever since the moon was two days old, the <name
                    type="NATIONALITY" n="German">Germans</name> haven't missed a single night and
                as soon as it gets dark, we hear the ominous whirr. At once the peace and quiet
                evaporate as if by magic and the whole atmosphere becomes alive with expectation and
                silent fears. The church bell is set ringing furiously and the doleful sirens begin
                their wailing from several parts of the town at once. Windows are thrown open and
                people begin to call back and forth to each other. This lasts only a few moments and
                then complete and utter silence. Every one has gone below ground and the town lies
                waiting in the moonlight.</p>

            <p>At first I refused to take refuge <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">dans la cave</etc>
                <etc type="PARENTHESES">the cellar</etc> partly because I didn't want to be
                smothered to death beneath the plaster and brick walls of the house. A direct hit
                seemed infinitely preferable to that, also, strange as it may seem, I had no desire
                to get out of bed. I had lost so much sleep and had been working so hard, that night
                generally found me thankful for a bed. Even if the noise of guns kept me awake I
                could rest, and the moist, chilly cellar held no charms! However, I found that
                staying <etc type="QUOTATION-MARK">au lit</etc> in the midst of an air raid was
                unheard of in these parts and Madame M. rushed into my room and with tears in her
                eyes implored me to accompany her below. The poor little old lady fears the avions
                above all else and the sound of their motors drives her into a frenzy of fear. In
                order to calm her I threw on a few clothes and we stumbled down the narrow stairs
                and spent the dark hours huddled in a little group around a candle that sputtered
                and flickered in the draughty, damp air. Our party consists always of Madame,
                Joséphine, a <name type="NATIONALITY" n="French">French</name> officer, who is
                likewise billeted in the house, and myself. The first night that we spent in the
                cellar, he was already below when we ladies arrived. I have never seen a more droll
                figure and I wonder now how I ever kept my face straight. He was attired in pink and
                white pajamas and on his head at a jaunty angle sat his most dressy uniform cap
                covered with gold braid and pale blue broadcloth! Undoubtedly he felt it added
                dignity and a certain modesty to his appearance. As we came down he was pacing up
                and down the mud floor in his bare feet! He told me that he had been through four
                years of war, had seen comrades blown to atoms right beside him.<etc
                    type="QUOTATION-MARK">I know what these bombs can do, I have seen with my two
                    eyes, it is folly not to seek shelter in a raid, so when I hear the <name
                        type="NATIONALITY" n="German">Boches</name> coming, I leap from my bed et je
                    me sauve, Mademoiselle.</etc> I felt that he was right and that the <name
                    type="NATIONALITY" n="French">French</name> must be thinking some of us very
                children who are still taking war as a game, and looking upon our folly and daring
                as bravery. Surely no one has any business to waste his life. For the first and
                perhaps the last time our lives are infinitely important and useful.</p>

            <p>This officer is really a very good sort and entertains us during the long hours with
                tales of all sorts. We discuss the war at great length and try and keep our minds
                occupied and off of the terrible sounds overhead. It's great for my <name
                    type="LANGUAGE" n="French">French</name> and I am improving. Sometimes the noise
                is deafening, the anti-air-craft guns keep up a continuous fire and yet the <name
                    type="NATIONALITY" n="German">Germans</name> don't seem to be the least bit
                daunted and fly just above the tops of the trees, placing their bombs with the most
                pitiless accuracy. <when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-23">Last night</when> three
                houses in this neighborhood were hit and in the old mill, half a block away, a young
                woman and her little girl were killed. It was a ghastly few hours. Madame had one
                fit of hysterics right after another and threw herself about the cellar in a spasm
                of fear, trembling violently and moaning and crying. It was one of the most pathetic
                and terrible sights I have ever seen. We tried to quiet her but as the bombs were
                literally falling all about us, there wasn't much one could say to cheer her. When
                one plane had dropped its supply of horror it would dash back and in ten minutes
                another would be swooping and sailing above us and the crash and uproar would begin
                again. In order that they may see better to do their hideous work, they drop a flare
                which illuminates the town as though it were day. By the time the strong light has
                burned itself out several bombs can be neatly placed.</p>

            <p>The raid generally begins about <when type="TIME" time="21:00">nine o'clock</when>
                and the planes come over in rapid succession until dawn. It is extraordinary what an
                effect the sound of the <name type="NATIONALITY" n="German">German</name> motor has
                upon one. The noise even at a great distance will wake me out of a sound sleep
                whereas our own planes can fly right past my window and I never know it.</p>

            <p>This morning the town is really upset. <when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-23">Last
                    night</when>'s raid was the worst yet. Two of our soldiers in the <name
                    type="BUILDING" n="Evacuation-Hospital">Evacuation Hospital</name> were killed
                and a great number of <name type="NATIONALITY" n="French">French</name>. A bomb lit
                across the street from the <name type="ORG" n="YMCA">Y</name> and this morning I
                found all my canteen windows smashed into a thousand pieces. The <name
                    type="NATIONALITY" n="German">Boches</name> dropped several notes all over the
                streets written in <name type="LANGUAGE" n="French">French</name> which said <etc
                    type="QUOTATION-MARK">If you think <when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-23">last
                        night</when>'s raid a bad one, wait for <when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-24"
                        >to-night</when>. We will break all records.</etc> The consequence is that
                the morale is not very good, every one worn out with no sleep, horror piled on
                horror, and the anticipation of worse things <when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-24"
                    >to-night</when>.</p>

            <p>Later -Same day.</p>

            <p><when type="SAYING" date="1918-7-24">To-day</when> is a sizzler, quite the worse
                we've had. The dust pours in at the windows and the canteen is black with flies.
                We've been making lemonade for hundreds of hot, tired soldiers. They come in white
                with dust and the perspiration running down their cheeks. No cotton uniforms to be
                issued this summer; the boys have to wear their woolly winter ones, poor darlings,
                and can't even take their blouses off. The result is that if this weather continues
                the entire <name type="ORG" n="American-Expeditionary-Forces">A. E. F.</name> will
                be reduced to a grease spot!</p>

            <p>We have made a hundred and sixty liters of lemonade <when type="SAYING"
                    date="1918-7-24">to-day</when>; the canteen has been jammed to the doors since
                early morning with men, tongues hanging out and clammering for something <etc
                    type="QUOTATION-MARK">cold and wet.</etc> The boys stand around in a huge ring
                while we make the lemonade, offering all kinds of advice and suggestions; I have
                quite a time keeping them on the other side of the counter; they all want to help
                but we can't use more than three stalwart and professional lemon squeezers! When the
                huge tank is finally filled, there are loud cheers from all present and it is worth
                anything to see the gusto with which they dispatch the lemonade down their dusty
                throats.</p>

            <p>How I love this place, -it's perfectly great being attached to a division.</p>

            <p><name type="PERSON" n="Westy">Westy</name>, <name type="PERSON" n="Alice"
                    >Alice</name>, <name type="PERSON" n="Squibby">Squibby</name>, who have canteens
                in little villages nearby, are in here quite frequently and we compare notes and
                discuss methods, and our various problems at length. I imagine some of us will
                shortly be sent back to <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Aix">Aix</loc> as our
                month of change is nearing its end. I can't tell you how I hate the thought of
                leaving, although of course I want to be where I am most needed. The simplicity of
                this place is a great contrast to <loc type="CITY" country="FRANCE" n="Aix"
                    >Aix</loc> and does appeal to me so much more than the gay whirl down there with
                the Casino and all its marble halls and broad terraces. There the boys come and go
                and you do all you can to cheer them, but here they aren't on leave and are up
                against the real thing, and, if possible, need a bit of feminine companionship more
                than anywhere else. Also one belongs to a unit and after a while you come to feel a
                very distinct sense of proprietorship, your hopes and fears and special prayers are
                centered about the men of your outfit and their failures and successes are very much
                your own. O! I do hope that the <name type="ORG" n="YMCA">Y</name> will let me stay
                right where I am. I have made up my mind of course to be a good soldier whatever
                comes, but I am hoping, hoping hard every minute that I shall be allowed to
                stay.</p>
        </letter>
    </letters>
</xml>
